<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-30T17:08:51-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Matt Skarha</title><subtitle>Your description here</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Integer Programming for Optimal Right Hand Guitar Fingerings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20181217/fingerings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Integer Programming for Optimal Right Hand Guitar Fingerings" /><published>2018-12-17T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-12-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20181217/fingerings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20181217/fingerings">&lt;h2 id=&quot;integer-programming-for-optimal-right-hand-guitar-fingerings&quot;&gt;Integer Programming for Optimal Right Hand Guitar Fingerings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Western canon of European classical music includes a substantial amount of scale-based, fingerstyle guitar music. When presented with a piece of sheet music, a classical guitarist must make a number of decisions regarding its performance. These decisions include notating the tablature, the left hand fingerings, and the right hand fingerings. This process, especially for right hand guitar fingerings, is often a trivial, yet cumbersome task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/dmc6KV0_UVM?t=273&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;III. Allegro Solemne&lt;/em&gt; movement&lt;/a&gt; from the 1921 piece “La Catedral” by Paraguayan composer Agustín Barrios. Due to its fast tempo, the performer must pay careful attention to the fingerings to adhere to proper technique while maintaining such a tempo. The problem then becomes how can we use math and computer science to determine optimal fingerings for this type of music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernd Tahon began to answer this question with this 2017 Master’s thesis &lt;a href=&quot;https://vibeserver.net/scripties/2017/Fingers%20to%20Frets%20-%20Master%20Thesis%20Bernd%20Tahon.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fingers to frets - A Mathematical Approach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where he examined how to utilize math and computer science to optimize left hand finger assignments. In this project, we tackled the separate, yet related problem of right hand finger assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fingerstyle music, the guitar is played using the thumb, index, middle, and ring fingers (not the pinky). At present, there is a notion within the classical guitar community of “proper right hand technique” which can be thought of as a set of rules that describe the physically optimal way of using the right hand to play scale-based, fingerstyle guitar music. These rules can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not repeat fingers on consecutive notes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The thumb plays the bassline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fingers stay in natural resting position&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid backwards crossings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid ring-middle-ring alternation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We decided to formulate this problem as an integer program where each of these rules are a constraint imposed by the model. The integer program, then, consists of a minimization of a sum of penalty terms that are incurred by violating the “soft” constraints. The complete integer program can be found below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/%5Ctext%7Bminimize%7D&quot; alt=&quot;\text{minimize}&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/%5Csum_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5E%7Bn%7D%20p%5E%7BBC%7D_i%20%2B%20p%5ET_i%20%2B%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%20p%5EF_i&quot; alt=&quot;\sum_{i=1}^{n} p^{BC}_i + p^T_i + \frac{1}{2} p^F_i&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/%5Ctext%7Bsubject%20to%3A%7D&quot; alt=&quot;\text{subject to:}&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/b_i*f_i%3C4%2Bp%5ET_i%20%5Cqquad%20%5Cforall%20%5C%20i&quot; alt=&quot;b_i*f_i&amp;lt;4+p^T_i \qquad \forall \ i&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/%7Cf_i-s_i%7C%20-%20(t_i*M)%20%5Cleq%20p_i%5EF%20%5Cqquad%20%5Cforall%20%5C%20i&quot; alt=&quot;|f_i-s_i| - (t_i*M) \leq p_i^F \qquad \forall \ i&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/-(s_i-s_%7Bi%2B1%7D)(f_i-f_%7Bi%2B1%7D)%5Cleq%20M*p%5E%7BBC%7D_i%20%5Cqquad%20%5Cforall%20%5C%20i%20%3C%20n-1&quot; alt=&quot;-(s_i-s_{i+1})(f_i-f_{i+1})\leq M*p^{BC}_i \qquad \forall \ i &amp;lt; n-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/f_i%20%2B%20f_%7Bi%2B1%7D%20%2B%20f_%7Bi%2B2%7D%20%5Cgeq%205%20%5Cqquad%20%5Cforall%20%5C%20i%20%3C%20n-2&quot; alt=&quot;f_i + f_{i+1} + f_{i+2} \geq 5 \qquad \forall \ i &amp;lt; n-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://tex.s2cms.ru/svg/%7Cf_i-f_%7Bi%2B1%7D%7C%20%5Cgeq%201%20%5Cqquad%20%5Cforall%20%5C%20i%20%3C%20n-1&quot; alt=&quot;|f_i-f_{i+1}| \geq 1 \qquad \forall \ i &amp;lt; n-1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An explanation of this model as well as other information about this project can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/RHFingerings.pdf&quot;&gt;this paper.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We implemented the model with Gurobi Optimizer and tested it on some selected measures of “La Catedral”. Below are some examples of the results. The f &lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; correspond to the finger assignment of each note as returned by our model and the f &lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt;* correspond to the optimal finger assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/measure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; style=&quot;float: center;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/measure2.png&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; style=&quot;float: center;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/measure3.png&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; style=&quot;float: center;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mskarha/rhfingerings&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to access the Github repository of the Python code used to generate the .lp file in order to use our model on your own music.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">Integer Programming for Optimal Right Hand Guitar Fingerings</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20171203/laser-interferometry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization" /><published>2017-12-03T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2017-12-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20171203/laser-interferometry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20171203/laser-interferometry">&lt;h2 id=&quot;laser-interferometry-for-loudspeaker-characterization&quot;&gt;Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this experiment, I set up Michelson interferometer to measure the frequency response of a commercial loudspeaker to high precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Michelson interferometer, a light source (in our case, a He-Ne laser) is split into two arms with a beam splitter. Each of those beams is reflected back towards the beamsplitter via a mirror, which then combines their amplitudes using the superposition principle. The resulting interference pattern is then picked up by a photoelectric detector. Because of the small wavelength of our light, this technique can be used to measure extremely small displacements, in accordance with the path length difference between the two arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to mount one of the mirrors on the cone of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jblpro.com/www/products/recording-broadcast/3-series/lsr305#.W4wu8NhKiRs&quot;&gt;JBL LSR305&lt;/a&gt; studio monitor that I use for mixing music. One of the main principles behind studio monitors is that the frequency response of the speakers must be as flat as possible so as to provide the most pure representation of whatever sound is being played. This is crucial for audio engineers who are dealing with very minute details in a recording. Typically, manufacturers of home stereo systems and other speakers go at great lengths to enhance audio quality by boosting certain bass, mid, and high frequencies. This renders normal speakers almost useless for audio production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this experimental setup, I was able to verify the flatness of the JBL LSR305 studio monitor by sweeping through a large range of frequencies and determining the cone displacement based on the interference pattern. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/Laser interferometric characterization for a vibrating speaker system good.pdf&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a paper I wrote about the experimental process. Check out this image of the experimental setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/michelson.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; style=&quot;float: center;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;My proudest snapchat moment ever was when I set up a laser interferometer in physics lab to measure speaker cone displacement then played technotronic&amp;#39;s pump up the jam and took data with an oscilloscope built by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tektronix?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@tektronix&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Tu06GeEF6M&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Tu06GeEF6M&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; skorched earth policy (@skarhaha56) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/skarhaha56/status/1012424839993413632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20170831/lorem-ipsum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer" /><published>2017-08-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-08-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20170831/lorem-ipsum</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20170831/lorem-ipsum">&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaotic-double-pendulum-synthesizer&quot;&gt;Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer is an attempt to find musicality in the laws of physics that govern our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The double pendulum is a simple idea, but complex mathematically. The basic idea of a chaotic double pendulum is that it is a simple physical system (a pendulum attached to the end of another pendulum) that exhibits rich dynamic behavior (much more interesting motion that one would expect) with a strong sensitivity to initial conditions. The motion is often described by physicists as unexpectedly mesmerizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to capture that mesmerizing motion with electroacoustic music using Max/MSP motion tracking and sound processing. By feeding data about the position, velocity, and acceleration of the pendulums into a series of oscillators, we can “listen” to the chaos that governs some of the laws of physics of our universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://scienceworld.wolfram.com/physics/DoublePendulum.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about some of the math behind coupled pendula. Additionally, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AwT0k09w-jw&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to watch a demo of a chaotic double pendulum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click the image below to watch a brief demo of the synthesizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Op3IMovg4CM&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img.youtube.com/vi/Op3IMovg4CM/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;synth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mskarha/Chaotic-Double-Pendulum-Synthesizer&quot;&gt;Github Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer</summary></entry></feed>