<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-11-29T12:17:40-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Matt Skarha</title><subtitle>Your description here</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20171203/laser-interferometry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization" /><published>2017-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20171203/laser-interferometry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20171203/laser-interferometry">&lt;h2 id=&quot;laser-interferometry-for-loudspeaker-characterization&quot;&gt;Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this experiment, I set up Michelson interferometer to measure the frequency response of a commercial loudspeaker to high precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Michelson interferometer, a light source (in our case, a He-Ne laser) is split into two arms with a beam splitter. Each of those beams is reflected back towards the beamsplitter via a mirror, which then combines their amplitudes using the superposition principle. The resulting interference pattern is then picked up by a photoelectric detector. Because of the small wavelength of our light, this technique can be used to measure extremely small displacements, in accordance with the path length difference between the two arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to mount one of the mirrors on the cone of my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jblpro.com/www/products/recording-broadcast/3-series/lsr305#.W4wu8NhKiRs&quot;&gt;JBL LSR305&lt;/a&gt; studio monitor that I use for mixing music. One of the main principles behind studio monitors is that the frequency response of the speakers must be as flat as possible so as to provide the most pure representation of whatever sound is being played. This is crucial for audio engineers who are dealing with very minute details in a recording. Typically, manufacturers of home stereo systems and other speakers go at great lengths to enhance audio quality by boosting certain bass, mid, and high frequencies. This renders normal speakers almost useless for audio production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this experimental setup, I was able to verify the flatness of the JBL LSR305 studio monitor by sweeping through a large range of frequencies and determining the cone displacement based on the interference pattern. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/docs/Laser interferometric characterization for a vibrating speaker system good.pdf&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a paper I wrote about the experimental process. Check out this image of the experimental setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/michelson.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; style=&quot;float: center;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;My proudest snapchat moment ever was when I set up a laser interferometer in physics lab to measure speaker cone displacement then played technotronic&amp;#39;s pump up the jam and took data with an oscilloscope built by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tektronix?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@tektronix&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Tu06GeEF6M&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Tu06GeEF6M&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; skorched earth policy (@skarhaha56) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/skarhaha56/status/1012424839993413632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 28, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">Laser Interferometry for Loudspeaker Characterization</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/20170831/lorem-ipsum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer" /><published>2017-08-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/20170831/lorem-ipsum</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/20170831/lorem-ipsum">&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaotic-double-pendulum-synthesizer&quot;&gt;Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer is an attempt to find musicality in the laws of physics that govern our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The double pendulum is a simple idea, but complex mathematically. The basic idea of a chaotic double pendulum is that it is a simple physical system (a pendulum attached to the end of another pendulum) that exhibits rich dynamic behavior (much more interesting motion that one would expect) with a strong sensitivity to initial conditions. The motion is often described by physicists as unexpectedly mesmerizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to capture that mesmerizing motion with electroacoustic music using Max/MSP motion tracking and sound processing. By feeding data about the position, velocity, and acceleration of the pendulums into a series of oscillators, we can “listen” to the chaos that governs some of the laws of physics of our universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://scienceworld.wolfram.com/physics/DoublePendulum.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about some of the math behind coupled pendula. Additionally, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AwT0k09w-jw&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to watch a demo of a chaotic double pendulum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click the image below to watch a brief demo of the synthesizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Op3IMovg4CM&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img.youtube.com/vi/Op3IMovg4CM/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;synth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mskarha/Chaotic-Double-Pendulum-Synthesizer&quot;&gt;Github Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">Chaotic Double Pendulum Synthesizer</summary></entry></feed>